So we pick up on דף מ"ט, Daf Mem Tet, 49, מ"ט
עמוד א', Mem Tet Amud Aleph, five lines from the top, and
we've been dealing exactly with this issue about needles found inside of
organs, and do we decide, do we assume that they came through
without creating holes? They came through the trachea or through the esophagus
or whatever? Or did we assume that they came from the outside
and punctured their way in? And the most recent discussion was whether
it was point first or head first. And if it was point
first and the head was pointing into the sort of cavity of
the body, then obviously it did not come through like the, you
know, through the either trachea and that system or through the esophagus
and the digestive system, but it obviously came, got punctured its way
through and made a hole somewhere and therefore would be a problem.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues with this, five lines from the
top. ההוא מחטא דאשתכח בסימפונא רבא דכבדא. Hahu machta de-ishtachach be-simpona raba
de-kavda.
So there was a מחטא, machta, a needle that was found in
the major tube, again I don't know a more technical term, leading
into the liver. Remember by the way the גמרא Gemara assumes that
the respiratory system, that it feeds, you know, goes from the trachea
into the lungs, but it also breaks off from the major trachea
and goes into the liver and the heart, that those were associated
with the breathing in the גמרא's Gemara understanding of anatomy. So this,
this tube into the liver would have branched off in the גמרא's
Gemara understanding from the trachea. Okay, so now you found this in
the tube of the liver. Now remember by the way also that
a hole in the liver is not a problem. Most of the
liver can be missing and it could still be a טריפה. treifa.
So let's take a look. So actually you're in good territory here.
If it came through the trachea you're okay. Even if it made
a hole in the trachea you're okay. A trachea is only a
problem with רוב. rov. And if it made a hole in the
liver you're okay. So the only problem is if it came in
through some other way and made a hole through let's say the
esophagus. That would have been a טריפה. treifa. So let's take a
look. ההוא מחטא דאשתכח בסימפונא רבא דכבדא. Hahu machta de-ishtachach be-simpona raba
de-kavda.
It was found in this major tube of the liver. הונא מר
בריה דרב אידי טריף. Huna Mar brei de-Rav Idai tareif.
So הונא Huna the son of רב אידי Rav Idai made it,
said it was a טריפה. treifa. רב אדא בר מניומי מכשר. Rav
Adda bar Minyomi machshir. רב אדא בר מניומי Rav Adda bar Minyomi
said it was כשר. kasher. אתו שיילוה לרבינא. Atu shailuh le-Ravina. They
asked רבינא. Ravina. אמר להו Amar le-hu so he said to them,
שקולו גלימא דטרפאי. Shekulu glima de-trefai. Go take the cloak away from
those that said it was a טריפה, treifa, meaning if on the
basis of them saying it was טריפה treifa they fed the animal
to the dogs and the owner's now lost out a whole cow,
so their פסק psak was totally wrong and they have to reimburse
the owners and so basically seize their garments in order to reimburse
the owners. So not only was he obviously פסק'ינג paskening that it
was כשר, kasher, but he was obviously very strongly פסק'ינג paskening that
way to speak about how how wrong the פסק psak would be
otherwise. Because again here you know whether how and the only possible,
in a whether it came through regardless of the holes it might
have made in the trachea and in the and in the liver
etc. it's not a problem. It's only a problem if it came
through making a hole in the esophagus and presumably we have rejected
that position and under normal circumstances we are not concerned that it
came through making a hole in the esophagus.
It is just being written here metaphorically right? They don't actually חייב
chayav forfeitures are they?
Presumably.
Well that's a גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Usually you're not חייב
chayav unless you actually seize the property and throw it to the
dogs, right presumably he meant it much more metaphorically. Okay. ההוא קשיותא
דאשתכח במרתא. Hahu kashishta de-ishtachach be-marta. There was a basically like a
nut, רש"י Rashi says it's a date nut, but one wonders if
we're not really talking about gallstones. I'm sure somebody there can enlighten
me about the exact reality of gallstones, but basically here's what it
say, you had a date nut in a gallbladder. Could this be
gallstones?
Totally. Okay, but they assumed that this was an actual date nut.
So let's take a look. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, כי
הוינא בי רב כהנא, ki haveina be-Rav Kahana, so אמר, amar, האי
ודאי סימפונא נקט ואתאי. hai vadai simpona nakat ve-asai. This definitely came
from the סימפון, simpon, that definitely came from the presumably
the gallbladder is near the liver, so it came, it came through
the trachea and through that whole branched tube system, again assuming that
the trachea breaks off into the liver. So it came from the
trachea, branched into with a tube into the liver, and from the
liver into the gallbladder, and that's where this came and it's not
a problem because it did not make a hole on its way
getting into the gallbladder. האי ודאי סימפונא נקט ואתאי. Hai vadai simpona
nakat ve-asai. אף על גב דלא קא נפקא, Af al gav de-lo
ka nafka,
and even though now it's so big that if you tried to
squeeze this nut, not nut, what would you call it, a stone,
essentially that's right that's what you call the seed of a date,
anyway this stone, if you tried to squeeze it out of the
tube, it would not go out, so it's too big, so how
could I assume it came through a tube? Nevertheless, where were we?
מירוול
הוא דריוילא. Mervel hu de-ravlei. Nevertheless it sort of, sort of squeezed
its way in. Meaning the way רש"י Rashi says is that yes
it's a little, it's bigger than the tube. but as the animal,
it gets stuck in the animal's tube and it slowly as the
animal moves, it slowly moves its way down, even though it's a
little bit too big. But now if you try to squeeze it
out, you won't, but that doesn't mean that it didn't get there
slowly over a lot, you know, over slow movement. רש״י Rashi says
the word מירבו mirvu is like a sieve, you know, when you
take a sieve, you have to constantly shake your hands to get
the stuff to go through. So here too, you know, the stone
worked its way through and finally got into the gallbladder. That's how
it's assuming it got there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, though
as I said, it probably is more likely to be referring to
a gallstone. So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, והני מילי דדיקלא,
vehani mili d'dikla, that's only if it is the stone of a
date from a palm tree. אבל דזיתא, aval d'zeisa, if it is
an olive stone, מירזא בזא, mirza beza, then an olive stone is
pointed and sharp, so then we have to be concerned that it
did not come through the trachea into the liver into the gallbladder,
there we have to be concerned it actually tore and did make
a hole and got into the gallbladder that way. Now that's pretty
surprising
given
that the גמרא Gemara says before number one, we don't assume in
the immediate earlier case when there was a needle in the liver,
we assume it came through the trachea. Why here are we assuming
that it did not also come through the trachea even though it
had the potential of tearing? And number two, something this big, if
it was really going to tear, you'd think you'd see a pretty
major gaping hole somewhere.
So it's pretty
interesting, surprising. So רש״י Rashi says we're talking only according to the
opinion that we don't פסקן pasken like, that we haven't been talking
according to the opinion that we assume that things, foreign matter most
likely comes through the esophagus and if it gets somewhere else it
got there through tear. So that's only according to that מאן דאמר,
man d'amar, we don't rule that way. תוספות Tosafot says no, that
would be bizarre that the גמרא Gemara is now shifting to that
מאן דאמר. man d'amar. So תוספות Tosafot says that since olive stones
are unlikely to go easily through the esophagus, so therefore, or unlikely
to go easily, excuse me, through the trachea. So since it's as
rough as a needle is, it's more reasonable here that even if
normally you assume things can come through the trachea, that this came
through the esophagus. Again, it's very strange to think that something this
large is going to come through tear, make a hole in the
esophagus and come into the gallbladder without us seeing any other evidence
for that. So רש״י's Rashi read that at least this is according
to the position we don't פסקן pasken like makes it a little
bit better. Okay, so that's in terms of stones in the gallbladder
which might have not been stones, might have not been foreign matter
at all, but the גמרא Gemara assumes they are. Now the גמרא
Gemara shifts gears a little bit
to makes a little bit easier of a discussion to wrap this
up. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, למה נקרא שמו ריאה, lama
nikra shemo reyah, why is the lung called a ריאה? reyah? שמאירה
את העיניים. sheme'irah es ha'einayim. Little play on the words, reversing the
letters, it gives light to the eyes. If you eat from the
lungs, it's very healthy food and it helps your eyesight. So the
גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, they asked the question, אכילה
או על ידי סמנים? achila o al yedei samanim? Straight if you
eat the lung straight is it good for your eyes or only
if you treat it in a particular way with certain types of
other ingredients, not just spices,
what סמנים samanim means, like certain types of medicinal ingredients together with
the lungs will make it very healthy. So תא שמע, t'shema, come
and hear that דאמר רב הונא בר יהודה, d'amar Rav Huna bar
Yehuda, אווזא בזוזא, avza bezuza, you could you should if a duck
is going for a זוז, zuz, that's a pretty cheap duck, I'd
like to have that. Anyway, if a duck is going for a
זוז, zuz, וריאה דידה בארבעה, vereyah didah b'arba,
you'll pay for its lung four זוז. zuz. So the גמרא Gemara
says how could that be? אי סלקא דעתך לאכילה, isalka da'atach l'achila,
if the lung is because it's so healthy or whatever, it's worth
it to pay four זוז zuz for the lung. So the גמרא's
Gemara saying one minute, if you mean that you can eat the
lung straight and it's healthy, לינקטיה בזוזא וליכול, linka bezuz v'leyichol, buy
the whole duck for your זוז zuz and eat the lung. אלא,
Ella, so the גמרא Gemara says על ידי סמנים, al yedei samanim,
it must mean that it's only healthy when it's treated and gives
you this health benefit when it's treated with these medicinal types of
ingredients. And therefore it's much more expensive, either because the ingredients cost
more, or what רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says is that like only
one in a thousand people, it's a very rare talent to know
how to treat, how to make this type of a mixture and
therefore you're obviously have to pay seriously for it. Okay, so that's
a little דרש drash on the word ריאה. reyah. Now the גמרא
Gemara goes on,
where were we?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אינקבה ריאה היכא דממשמשא ידי דטבחא. inkava reyah heicha d'mamshesha yadei
d'tavcha. So you've got a hole in the lung but it's in
the place where it's handled by the שוחט. shochet. So the שוחט
shochet will take the lung and he'll whatever רש״י Rashi says, sometimes
maybe it means that accidentally he can touch it when
it's likely that the
שוחט *shochet* would have handled it directly and maybe the handling caused
a hole. So what do we say? תלינן או לא תלינן *Talinan
o lo talinan*? Do we do we do we like you
know lean hang it on the שוחט *shochet* or do we not
hang it on the שוחט *shochet*? Do we assume that the שוחט
*shochet* was the cause of this hole? So רב Rav אדא בר
נתן אמר תלינן *Rav Adda bar Natan amar talinan*. And רב Rav
אדא בר נתן *Rav Adda bar Natan* says we do you know
ascribe it to the שוחט *shochet*. מר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי אמר
לא תלינן *Mar Zutra breih deRav Mari amar lo talinan*. And the
other opinion is we do not ascribe it. והלכתא v'hilkhosa תלינן *Vehilchata
talinan*. And the הלכה halacha *halacha* is תלינן *talinan*, we do ascribe
it. So this is pretty fascinating if you think about it. Here
you have a hole right in front of you and we're just
going to say, yeah, but you know based on that's exactly where
the שוחט *shochet* handles it, so probably came from the שוחט *shochet*.
Whereas when you've got things like סירכא sircha *sircha*, you know, which
aren't even observable holes, there we'll say, oh, what we can assume
happened is there was a hole and the סירכא sircha *sircha* plugged
it, but the סירכא *sircha* is not a sufficient plug and therefore
it's a טרפה treifa *treifah*. So you know it's pretty interesting where
we, you know, what types of assumptions we make whether לחומרא *lechumra*
or לקולא *lekula* based on I guess you know our sort of
range of assumptions and likelihoods. So here, although we have a very
visible hole, if it's exactly where the שוחט *shochet* handles it, we
assume it's coming from the שוחט *shochet*. אמר שמואל בריה דרבי אבהו
*Amar Shmuel breih deRabbi Abbahu*, so שמואל *Shmuel* the son of רבי
rebbe? אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu* said: אבא *Abba*, my father, so רבי אבהו
*Rabbi Abbahu*, מרישי כלי דרפרם הוה *meireishei keili deRafram hava*. He was
from the head of the כלי *keili*, not כלי *kli*, כלי *keili*
of the gatherers of רפרם *Rafram*. So like מכילתא *Mechilta*, right, the
word מכילתא *Mechilta* which is a collection of the Tannaitic sayings on
שמות *Shemot*. The word ח-ל-ט *chet lamed tet* means to gather.
So כלי *keili* means to gather like so when he would gather
the people together to hear the דרשות *drashot* of of what's his
name,
I lost my place here, right, of רפרם *Rafram*. Thank you. So
anyway, so he was
רפרם's *Rafram's* like head דרשן *darshan* or gatherer of the people. הוה
ואמר *hava veamar* and he said presumably in the name of רפרם
*Rafram*, תלינן *talinan* that we do make that we do ascribe it
to the שוחט *shochet*. אמרוה להך קמיה דמר זוטרא בריה דרב מרי
*Amruha lehach kamei deMar Zutra breih deRav Mari* they said this over
to in the name to מר זוטרא *Mar Zutra* בריה דרב מרי
*breih deRav Mari* ולא קיבלה *velo kiblah*, he didn't accept it. אמר
רב amar Rav: משרשיא כוותיה דאבא מסתברא *Amar Rav Mesharshiya kevateih deAbba
mistabra*, like the father of אבא *Abba* makes sense, the father of
אבא *Abba* was רב Rav אדא בר נתן *Rav Adda bar Natan*
who says תלינן *talinan*, that makes sense. דהא תלינן בזאב *deha talinan
beze'ev*, we know that if a זאב *ze'ev* comes and takes a
you know one of the inner organs and returns it with holes
in it, we assume that it was the holes were made by
the זאב *ze'ev*. So here too we'll assume the holes are made
by, you know, the שוחט *shochet*. Of course you could imagine a
little different, a wolf takes something with its teeth which makes holes,
whereas a שוחט *shochet* handles things with its hands, but again the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that this is, you know, again I have
no idea I've never dealt with it but the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
assumes that this is a natural thing that if you're handling the
if you're handling it you might cause it to crack, you might
cause a hole to form. I would assume if there are visible
ways to identify you know if let's say something that was handled
through the hands was more a elongated tear than a circular hole,
I assume you would factor those issues in as well, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does say that when you have something specific to
ascribe it to and it's a reasonable thing to ascribe it to,
we will do that. Yes, there's a
question?
I was just going to say a שוחט *shochet* is working with
a knife, presumably.
Oh, that's true also. ורש"י *VeRashi*, I forgot to mention that, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* does, although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* before said the hands
of the שוחט *shochet*, ידי דטבחא *yadei detabcha*, ורש"י *VeRashi* did say
yes it's possible that when he was cutting up the animal if
his knife touched the lung, right, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* mentions that as
well. Okay, so מורנא *morna*, what about if there's a worm? If
there's a if there's a you see a worm hole in the
in the lung with a worm coming out of it. So do
we assume the worm that if it was made when the animal
is alive it would be like any other hole, but do we
assume it comes while it was alive or after death? So פליגי
בה רב יוסף בר דוסאי ורבנן *pligi bah Rav Yosef bar Dosai
verabbanan*, there was a debate. חד אמר קודם שחיטה פריש *chad amar
kodem shechitah parish*, we assume that the worm separated basically made the
hole after שחיטה *shechitah* and וחד אמר לאחר שחיטה פריש *vechad amar
le'achar shechitah parish* after, one said before, one said after, והלכתא לאחר
שחיטה פריש *vehilchata le'achar shechitah parish* and the הלכה halacha *halacha* is
לאחר שחיטה פריש *le'achar shechitah parish* we say that it separated after
שחיטה *shechitah* we assume, I don't know why, maybe because worms inside
of the animal you know they're not so common when the animal
is alive or they don't burrow that far. Anyway here we will
assume, or maybe even we don't know, but it's, you know, but
we can make it we have a specific thing like a worm
the same way you had a specific thing like a שוחט *shochet*,
we assume that it happened afterwards.
So wait, how much after שחיטה *shechitah* is it? Like you know
the שוחט *shochet* could cut it up and three days later you
see this worm, you're going to assume that the worm the whole
time the... Yeah, yeah, you're right.
I don't know that either and that's obviously an appropriate question to
ask, right? How much you look at other factors as well, you
know. So again the question is how much is this like a
formal issue, because you could understand it as a formal way because
we say basically that an animal that's שחט is בחזקת היתר bechezkas
hetter unless you have specific evidence of a טריפה. treifah. So maybe
here once you assume this type of a חזקת היתר, chezkas hetter,
then you have even when you have a specific thing, if you
have something to make it depend upon, so you make it depend
on that. Of course the problem is as you've been seeing, there's
been much, much more גמרא Gemara about the lungs issues than about
any other טריפה. treifah. And if you look in שלחן ערוך, Shulchan
Aruch, there's much bigger section, and lungs are really the only things
we check. And really the reason we check lungs is because of
the likelihood of holes or סירכות. sirchos. So once we are so
concerned about these problems, to just ascribe it somewhere else when you
have that ability
is not so פשוט. pashut. So you're right, if it's how much
do you need other supporting evidence or at least how much would
you factor in specific evidence in the opposite column, you would imagine
that you would, but it's not so clear from the גמרא. Gemara
I can't tell you למעשה, lema'aseh, I don't really deal with these
issues למעשה, lema'aseh, but it's a very good question. Okay, so now
we are finally done with the major discussion about lungs and we
just wrap it up now with the final opinion in the משנה
Mishnah of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that the hole has
to go into the actual sort of trachea area where the tubes
break off. Of course you realize that if we were to פסק
pasken like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we could ignore most of the
previous גמרא Gemara and a lot more animals wouldn't be
טריפה treifah because any סירכא in any of those issues would only
be a problem if they occurred in the major sort of tube
area. So let's take a look. רבי שמעון אומר עד שתינקב. Rabbi
Shimon omer ad she-tinkav. אמר רבה בר תחליפא אמר רב ירמיה בר
אבא, Amar Rabbah bar Tachlifa amar Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba, עד שתינקב
לסמפון גדול, ad she-tinkav l'simpon gadol, until it goes into the major
tube. Again I don't know if you have a picture there, but
I assume most people have a general picture in their head about
what how it looks like the lungs with this trachea and then
the tubes sort of feeding into the side sacs and the little
sacs, the אוני. onot. So he said it's not enough that it
goes into one of those tubes feeding into the tinier sacs, it
has to go into the major tube running down the middle. Okay,
so that's a pretty drastic limiting of the problem of טריפות treifos
in the lungs. יתיב רב אחא בר אבא קמיה דרב הונא. Yasiv
Rav Acha bar Abba kamei de-Rav Huna. Now by the way it's
interesting because remember a hole in the trachea is not a problem,
a hole in the lungs is a problem. So here although a
hole in the lung itself makes a problem, he says it's only
when the hole goes into that tube area within the lung, although
again in the trachea itself it would not be a problem. Okay,
so יתיב רב אחא בר אבא קמיה דרב הונא ויתיב וקאמר. yasiv
Rav Acha bar Abba kamei de-Rav Huna ve-yasiv ve-ka'amar. So he was
sitting in front of רב הונא Rav Huna and he was saying:
רבי
מלוך אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Meloch amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. Who ever heard of רבי מלוך Rabbi Meloch before? But okay.
רבי מלוך Rabbi Meloch said in the name of רבי יהושע בן
לוי: Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: הלכה כרבי שמעון. halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon. We
rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Wow, that is pretty radical. I
mean as I said, it would change major areas of טריפות. treifos.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, רב הונא
Rav Huna said back, מלוך ארבא קאמרת? Meloch Arva ka-amart? Who, מלוך
Meloch the Arab or the person from Arabia? אין הלכה כרבי שמעון
קאמר. ein halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ka-amar. I know what he says, he
didn't say the הלכה halacha was like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he
said the הלכה halacha was not like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You
misheard that tradition, I know what he says. So
כי סליק רבי זירא אשכחיה לרב ביבי דיתיב וקאמר. ki selik Rabbi
Zeira ashkechei le-Rav Bibi de-yasiv ve-ka'amar. So when רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
came up from went up to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he found
רב ביבי Rav Bibi who was sitting and saying: אמר רבי מלוך
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי הלכה כרבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Meloch amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon. Again a tradition in the
name of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi by this
רבי מלוך Rabbi Meloch that we rule like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said to him:
חיי דמר, Chayei d'mar, by the life of the master, meaning like
it's like an oath. דאנא ורבי חייא בר אבא ורב אסי איקלען
לאתריה דרבי מלוך, de-ana ve-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba ve-Rav Assi ikla'an l'asrei
de-Rabbi Meloch, that I and רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba and רב
אסי Rav Assi went to the place of רבי מלוך. Rabbi Meloch.
If I'm translating the word before correctly, that means it was like
Arabia, so that was a pretty serious trip.
Anyway, ואמרי ליה, ve-amrei lei, and we said to him: אי אמר
מר הלכה כרבי שמעון? ee amar mar halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon? We've heard
this tradition that you've been saying, but there's a major debate about
what the tradition is. So did the master say we rule like
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Is that what you said? ואמר לן, ve-amar
lan, he said back to us: אין הלכה כרבי שמעון אמי. ein
halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ami. No, I said the הלכה Halacha, is not
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
So therefore he said that,
so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira was now also correcting this teacher of
whoever it was,
of רב ביבי, Rav Bibi, and saying that I know that רבי
מלוך Rabbi Meloch actually said the הלכה Halacha is not like רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, don't quote him the other way. He said אין
הלכה
כרבי שמעון אמי. ein halacha ke-Rabbi Shimon ami. ואת מה בידך? ve-at
mah be-yadecha? So then whoever it was said back to רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira, so רב ביבי Rav Bibi said back to רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira,
he said okay, I hear what you said that רבי מלוך Rabbi
Meloch said, but what's your own personal position about this? He said
to רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira said: הכי אמר רבי יצחק בר אמי אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי. Hachi amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ami amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi.
Here's what רבי יצחק בר אמי Rabbi Yitzchak bar Ami says in
the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. lately
so you notice it's the same רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi they're quoting, הלכה כרבי שמעון. Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. So you
have a רבי מלאך, Rabbi Meloch, there's a debate what רבי מלאך
Rabbi Meloch said, some say he said it is הלכה, Halacha some
say it isn't, but regardless he said it in the name of
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. And here now רב
זירא Rav Zeira saying I have a tradition in the name of
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi that says the הלכה
is like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So you would think that's where
we would be headed, but then the גמרא Gemara. concludes,
ואין הלכה כרבי שמעון. v'ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon. Is the last line,
the גמרא Gemara has the last line, we do not say like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Of course, if we were to פסקן pasken
like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, the as I said the implications would
be radical, would mean that we would solve 90% of טרפות treifos
because so many are all all the טרפות treifos are basically about
סירכות sirchos in the lung. Now how is it that the גמרא
Gemara, reverses here at the end, or I don't know reverses, but
at least rejects these other things. If you look at רש"י Rashi
five lines from the bottom, ואין הלכה כרבי שמעון. v'ein halacha k'Rabbi
Shimon.
רש"י Rashi says גמרא קפסיק לה. Gemara ka pasik lei. This is
the גמרא Gemara sort of wrapping it up. ובישיבה האחרונה נפסקו הלכות
הללו הפסוקות סתם בגמרא. Ubiyeshiva ha'achronah nifsaku halakhos halalu hapsukos stam bagemara.
In the last convocation, right? In some later, you know, these final
הלכות Halachos were were ruled in the גמרא. Gemara, The הלכתא hilkhesa
in the גמרא Gemara. in general, right, are pretty are like the
latest layer of the גמרא, Gemara which is essentially what רש"י is
saying. It's not exactly clear how that developed. Did it develop through
some type of deliberation? Did it just develop because that became the
adopted practice? And once it's the adopted practice, you know, then that
sort of weighed in very heavily. Sometimes interestingly, הלכתא hilkhesa in the
גמרא Gemara are grafted in from the הלכות גדולות. Hilkhos Gedolos. That
the הלכות גדולות Hilkhos Gedolos brings out a discussion in the גמרא,
Gemara then the הלכות גדולות Hilkhos Gedolos says והלכתא X, meaning he
himself is ruling, and then in later editions that got re sort
of glossed
into the גמרא. Gemara But הלכתא hilkhesa are definitely a later layer,
and it really raises the question that Dov was asking before we
started, you know, about how exactly in the end of the day
does הלכה get פסקן, paskened, especially here, you know, what's fascinating is
everybody is is killing themselves for what this tradition of רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi is. Well what's their tradition? You
know, I mean obviously the question about is it a טרפה treifa.
in any part of the lung or only the central part would
seem, you know, seem like something that people would have a tradition
about, especially if you consider the fact that we've had all these
previous stories where people were checking lungs and various things, all of
them seem to strongly indicate we don't rule like it. So you
know that's I think that's number one fascinating like why was it
so critical finding out this one tradition, you know, what about any
other traditions or any other practices? And then at the end of
the day, what and then at the end of the day we
have two pretty much equally weighted voices, what רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said, or if anything it's like one and
a half to a half because even with all the various versions
it did seem like there was some that that maybe the reason
that there were different versions of what רבי מלאך Rabbi Meloch said
is because there were different versions of what רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said. So it also you know just leaves
open the question about how did the גמרא Gemara come to its
final conclusion, you know, again, unless that was just through how practice
evolved without some clear process or you know, but a lot of
this remains unclear. What was the comment?
No that there was especially given the fact that we're saying the
בבלי Bavli is more willing to take סברא sevara
than
tradition but you know here you have these people going to Caesarea
or wherever it is to find out what the tradition of רבי
מלאך Rabbi Meloch is which may not necessarily have been the tradition
of everyone else.
Right, so you know, and
yeah I understand exactly that's the point. So okay it's all very
nice that that's you know רבי יהושע בן לוי's Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi position, but that's my point like what about everyone else's position.
So a, the question about you know going back to the issue
we discussed before here about how much do you weigh a tradition
as opposed to סברא, sevara, but number two is also like this
is something that there's got to be other traditions in place because
these are the issues that come up every day, which is is
this a problem in the lung, you know, and from all the
other גמרא Gemara it sounds like it was clearly it clearly was
a problem because they were worried about all these lung issues, which
wouldn't have been an issue 90% of them if we פסקן pasken
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So I really don't know, you know,
I don't have more insight into this, I can just raise the
questions. Alright, so now we are finally done with the lungs, so
we can say ברוך שפטרני Baruch Shep'tarani on that, I mean that
as I said is the major area of focus for טרפות. treifos.
And now we are going to move on to the issue about
the קיבה, keiva, the stomach. This is the fourth of the stomachs
where the food goes after it's fully chewed up and where it
gets the digestive juices and which is most comparable to the stomach
of humans. So ניקבה הקיבה, nikva hakeiva, if there's a hole in
the קיבה keiva it's a טרפה. treifa So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יצחק בר נחמני אמר רבי יהושע, Amar
Rav Yitzchak bar Nachmani Amar Rabbi Yehoshua, חלב שעל גבי קיבה כהנים
נהגו בו היתר. chelev she'al gabei keiva kohanim nahagu bo heter.
So here we're going to get into a question which is actually
quite fascinating that there's not a more explicit discussions in the גמרא
Gemara in the משניות Mishnayos about this, about the forbidden חלב chelev
in the animal. What's considered to be חלב chelev and what's not.
So, you know, חלב chelev is obviously these huge like, you know,
collections of fat that are over the
organs, and different from שומן shuman which is permissible fat which is
like the type of stuff when you get a steak, you know,
that type of stuff in between
the... not that appetizing, but anyway huge collections of fat on top
of the organs, but even within the חלב, chelev, we're going to
find out that not all of it is forbidden. Primarily the חלב
chelev that is forbidden is the type of חלב chelev that was
offered as a קרבן. korban. So we're going to now digress and
not talk about טרפות treifos so much, but talk about what חלב
chelev is forbidden. We will circle back and talk about טרפות treifos
and whether חלב chelev can stop up holes and be a legitimate
way of stopping up holes. So let's take a look. Look, אמר
רבי יצחק בר פנחס אמר רבי יהושע חלב שעל גבי הקיבה, Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak bar Pinchas amar Rabbi Yehoshua chelev she'al gabei hakeiva, the
חלב chelev that's on the קיבה, keiva, כהנים נהגו בו היתר. kohanim
nahagu bo heter. The כהנים kohanim used to say that that was
permissible and that they could eat it. Now, as רש"י points out,
they had a vested interest in saying that because you would give
the כהן kohen the קיבה, keiva, that would be one of the
gifts from a slaughtered animal. So if you're giving them the
קיבה, keiva, you would give them the fat of the קיבה keiva
with it, because it would come clumped together with it. And therefore,
it would be very nice for them to say that that was
not forbidden fat and that they could use it. כרבי ישמעאל שאמר
משום אבותיו. KeRabbi Yishmael she'amar mishum avosav. And they were following the
position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that said in the name of
his fathers. And we'll see that in a minute, that that's permissible
fat. וסימנך, Vesimanchah, the way that you can remember it is, ישמעאל
כהנא מסייע כהני. Yishmael kahana mesaya kahanei. ישמעאל, Yishmael, who himself was
a כהן, kohen,
gave פסקים psakim that helped כהנים. kohanim. The גמרא Gemara presumably is
not questioning the integrity of his position, but at least pointing out
that this is a way to remember the way he paskened in
a number of ways, which is that a number of his פסקים
psakim actually benefit the כהנים. kohanim. Let's take a look. מאי היא?
Mai hi? Where do you see that other than this one case?
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: כה תברכו את בני
ישראל. Koh tevorchu es benei Yisrael. This is how you shall bless
בני ישראל. benei Yisrael. רבי ישמעאל אומר למדנו ברכה לישראל מפי כהנים.
Rabbi Yishmael omer lamadnu beracha leYisrael mipi kohanim. This tells us that
Israel is blessed from the כהנים. kohanim. לכהנים עצמם לא למדנו. Lekohanim
atzmam lo lamadnu. Where are the כהנים kohanim blessed? That's not in
this פסוק. pasuk. כשהוא אומר ואני אברכם, Keshehu omer va'ani avarechem, at
the end of it, this is how you shall bless the children
of Israel and I will bless them. Who are the them? הוי
אומר כהנים מברכים לישראל. Hevei omer kohanim mevorchim leYisrael. So he says
it means God will bless the כהנים. kohanim. כהנים Kohanim bless Israel,
והקדוש ברוך הוא מברך לכהנים, vehaKadosh Baruch Hu mevarech lakohanim, and God
will bless the כהנים. kohanim. So that's now, it's not exactly a
פסק, psak, but it's a very nice דרשה drasha in the פסוקים
pesukim in a way that the כהנים kohanim get a direct blessing
from God. People only get a blessing through the כהנים, kohanim, but
the כהנים kohanim get a direct blessing from God. That's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says no. למדנו ברכה לישראל מפי כהנים. Lamadnu beracha leYisrael
mipi kohanim. We see from the first פסוק pasuk that Israel is
blessed from the כהנים. kohanim. מפי גבורה לא למדנו. Mipi gevura lo
lamadnu. We don't see that the people are blessed by God. כשהוא
אומר ואני אברכם, Keshehu omer va'ani avarechem, I will bless them, them
meaning according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the people, הוי אומר כהנים
מברכים לישראל. hevei omer kohanim mevorchim leYisrael. The כהנים kohanim bless Israel,
והקדוש ברוך הוא מסכים על ידם. vehaKadosh Baruch Hu maskim al yadam.
And God then says, oh, you're going to bless the people, now
I will bless the people too, I will agree with your blessing.
So it's the people are being blessed by God and the כהנים
kohanim are not being blessed at all, according to this. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא לרבי עקיבא ברכה לכהנים מנא ליה? Ela leRabbi
Akiva beracha lakohanim mena lei? Where does he get the idea that
the כהנים kohanim get a ברכה? beracha? Because presumably, they deserve a
ברכה beracha the same way the people do, so where is their
ברכה beracha coming from?
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק מאברכך מברכיך. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
me'avarchacha mevorachecha. I will bless those who bless you, the blessing to
אברהם. Avraham. So since the כהנים kohanim bless you, I will also
bless the כהנים. kohanim. But of course, that is not as nice
as רבי ישמעאל'ס Rabbi Yishmael's דרשה, drasha, because in רבי ישמעאל'ס Rabbi
Yishmael's דרשה, drasha, first of all, the כהנים kohanim got it straight
from God, and the people only got it from the כהנים. kohanim.
So the כהנים kohanim were on a higher level. Number one. Number
two is it said it was sort of like the same blessing.
Here, it's much more derivative. Oh, anybody who gives you a blessing,
they'll also be blessed, but it's not necessarily like they're included in
the same blessing. תוספות Tosafos points out, it seems to be as
an aside, but there's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says that this idea,
whoever blesses you will be blessed, is not limited to Jews. Anybody
who blesses the Jewish people, even non-Jews, will be blessed. So again,
תוספות Tosafos isn't making this point, but I'll make this point. So
then it's not again something special about the כהנים kohanim if they're
just included in this very generic I'll give a blessing to whoever
blesses you. So obviously, רבי ישמעאל'ס Rabbi Yishmael's דרשה drasha is a
lot nicer. Okay, so that, ומאי מסייע לכהנים? vemai mesaya lakohanim? So
therefore, or what does it mean that he helped the כהנים? kohanim?
So
the
גמרא Gemara is now saying, if everybody agrees that the כהנים kohanim
get a ברכה, beracha, how is his דרשה drasha any better?
דמוקמי לה לברכת כהנים במקום ברכה דישראל. Demokmi lah levirchas kohanim bimkom
beracha deYisrael. He puts the blessing of the כהנים kohanim together with
the blessing of Israel. They're included in the same blessing, it's not
just derivative or very
generic whoever blesses you is blessed. Okay, so that's where he had
one דרשה drasha that was nice to the כהנים. kohanim. Now back
to our point, רבי ישמעאל שאמר משום אבותיו מאי היא? Rabbi Yishmael
she'amar mishum avosav mai hi? What about that statement that we said
in the name of his fathers that he said about the fat,
that the fat of the קיבה keiva is permissible? דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: braisa: ואת כל החלב אשר על הקרב ואת
כל החלב אשר בקרב. ve'es kol hachelev asher al hakerev ve'es kol
hachelev asher bekerev. And all the fat that is on the inner
insides, and all the fat that is in the insides. This is
put up on the altar. So this extra פסוק pasuk ואת ve'et
and all is coming to include even some extra fat that's not
like in the sort of central cavity. So what is that coming
to include? And again with the assumption that the fat that's on
the מזבח mizbe'ach is what is forbidden for ישראל Yisrael to eat.
So the גמרא Gemara says or the ברייתא beraita says להביא חלב
של הדקין lehavi chelev shel hadakin דברי רבי ישמעאל, divrei Rabbi Yishmael,
that includes the fat on the small intestines, that's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר omer להביא חלב שעל גבי
הקיבה, lehavi chelev she'al gabei hakeiva,
to include the fat that is on the קיבה, keiva, this last
of the four stomachs. So presumably this is what goes on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
this is what goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but also if it
goes on the מזבח mizbe'ach then it's also forbidden to ישראל. Yisrael.
So, and we're also assuming by the way that we'll see in
a minute that they are of different consistencies, that there's a different
really physical type of a fat. But if you say that it
includes the fat on the קיבה, keiva, you'll certainly want to include
the fat on the small intestine. But if you say the fat
on the small intestine, you will not include the fat on the
קיבה. keiva. So again, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is implicitly saying here
that the fat on the קיבה keiva is not forbidden, and that
is again this supporting position that's very nice for the כהנים kohanim
that the fat of the קיבה keiva is not forbidden. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, uraminihu, one minute, but I'll ask
you on this.
If you look at the side it's ואת כל החלב אשר על
הקרב, ve'et kol hachelev asher al hakerev, and all the fat that
is on the inside. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר, omer, so here
we're going to say how to know which fat is forbidden and
which is not, or which goes on the altar, which does not.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר omer מה חלב המכסה את הקרב קרום
ונקלף אף כל קרום ונקלף. ma chelev hamichaseh et hakerev krum veniklaf
af kol krum veniklaf.
The same way the major fat that's on the inside of the
animal has a type of a קרום, krum, has a type of
a what's it called, like a skin to it, you know, and
that can be peeled. So it's not just one consistency. There's a
membrane, I guess would be the right thing, you know, there's some
type of a membrane that surrounds it, and if you peel off
that membrane, then you get the gushy fat on the inside. So
that's the type of fat that is biblically forbidden, that's חלב. chelev.
That's what, that's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. I'm sorry, it's רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. If you look at the side it's רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael because the גמרא Gemara is clearly going to have a
problem that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael contradicts himself. So that's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר omer no, מה
חלב המכסה את הקרב, ma chelev hamichaseh et hakerev, no, no, the
major fat on the inside has three characteristics: תותב קרום ונקלף. totav
krum veniklaf. Not only does it have this membrane that can be
peeled, but it also is תותב, totav, which is literally means it's
a cloak. And the way רש״י Rashi explains it what it means
is basically it's sort of like is, it's sort of like a
cloak around an organ, it sits on top of the organs and
it cloaks them, but it's not like sticky and adhesive to them,
so more, you know, so it's more like something that is distinct
and separate but surrounds and sheathes them, cloaks them. So that's what
he says. So by adding this criteria, he is going to exclude
certain things from being חלב. chelev. And one thing that gets excluded
from being חלב chelev if you add this criteria of cloaking is
the חלב chelev on the קיבה, keiva, because the חלב chelev on
the קיבה keiva has this membrane and it sticks, but it doesn't,
and it has this membrane, but it sticks and it doesn't cloak.
So according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva now, the חלב chelev on
the קיבה keiva would not be a problem. Although before, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said the חלב chelev on the קיבה keiva is a
problem. So we have a contradiction, and presumably רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
also is reversed. So the גמרא Gemara says how do you deal
with it?
So שלח רבין משמיה דרבי יוחנן, shlach Ravin mishmei deRabbi Yochanan, so
רבין Ravin sent in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, כך
היא הצעה של משנה, kach hi hatza'ah shel mishna, this is the
layout of the משנה, mishna, meaning this teaching of the משנה mishna
the last one is correct, that is the correct
teaching, ואיפך קמייתא, ve'ipeich kamayta, but reverse the first one. The first
משנה mishna where they were explicitly debating not the characteristics, but does
it apply to just to the small intestine or even to the
קיבה? keiva? So the positions were reversed. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should
be the one saying the small intestine, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
is the one saying the קיבה. keiva. Because we see that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has more criteria and a smaller set than רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי חזית דהפכת קמייתא
איפוך בתרייתא? mai chazit dehapchat kamayta ipoch batrayta?
Why reverse the first teaching, where they're discussing קיבה keiva versus small
intestines? Reverse the second teaching, where they're discussing the defining characteristics? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, שני הכא כיון דקתני מה דוקא. shani
hacha kivan dekatani ma davka. Here since it said like, well, what's
the case? You know, and it specifically identifies characteristics, that it has
it can peel and it cloaks, etc. So that means that we're
being very precise. I don't know how that means
that, but somehow since we're precisely identifying characteristics, somehow we're also being
precise about remembering which opinion said which one. I don't know exactly
get that, but anyway we are reversing the first. So now we
have רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva as the more lenient, saying that it
needs to cloak, and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael as the stricter, and
therefore according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the חלב chelev of the
קיבה keiva is not a problem. According to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
it is. So now we're back to our issue that a minute
ago we said that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael in the name of
his אבותיו avotav said that the כהנים kohanim could eat the חלב
chelev that's on
the. The גמרא Gemara says אי הכי i hachi כרבי ישמעאל, keRabbi
Ishmael,
when we said that the כהנים kohanim would eat that חלב chelev
following רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, כרבי עקיבא היא, keRabbi Akiva hi, it’s
really following רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק—רב
נחמן בר יצחק says no, שאמר משום אבותיו ולאו סבירא ליה. she-amar
mishum avosav v’lei lo svira lei. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael was saying
in the name of his fathers that this is—that his fathers say,
here you get—again, here you go like you were asking before, here’s
a tradition where he personally doesn't hold like it and yet he's
reporting a family tradition. So his fathers say that this fat is
permissible; he personally was not of that opinion. He personally ruled that
the fat was forbidden. So again you don't have רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael personally necessarily being a big defender of the causes of the
כהנים, kohanim, because here it's only his fathers; he himself, the, you
know, he himself disagreed with that ruling. By the way, notice again
that ולאו סבירא ליה v’lei lo svira lei does not mean that
he doesn't have an opinion; it means that he actually rejects that
opinion. Okay, so now we have this question about whether the fat
of the קיבה keivah and really what are the characteristics of the
fat. Now we are going to turn it back into a discussion
about טרפות. treifos. So let's take a look. אמר רב:
חלב טהור סותם, טמא אינו סותם. chelev tahor soteim, tamei eino soteim.
So the חלב chelev that is טהור, tahor, that is not
forbidden, is—can fill up a hole. The טמא tamei one cannot. And
this actually goes exactly to the characteristics. Assuming like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that one of the characteristics is that it cloaks, which as
I said means it's sort of separate but surrounds, so that's as
opposed to חלב chelev which is not forbidden, which actually is much
more like adhesive. So because the non-forbidden חלב chelev is adhesive, that
can do a good job stopping up holes, and that actually will
solve a problem of holes. So here exactly, you know, we've had
cases before where sometimes you say membranes or whatever don't stop up
holes and טרפות treifos don't because they're going to tear off, etc.
Here we're saying that sometimes certain things would, like a nearby organ
could be on top of a hole and could seal it up.
So here we are saying the חלב chelev can seal it up,
but only the non-forbidden חלב chelev which is much more stickier. By
the way also if the forbidden חלב chelev has a membrane around
it, it's going to be less sticky than if it doesn't have
a membrane around it. So the non-forbidden חלב chelev is sticky and
will fill up holes; the forbidden one will not be able
to—I mean it might fill it up, but it won't solve the
problem because it's not going to be as permanent of a solution.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב ששת אומר אחד
זה ואחד זה סותם. Rav Sheshet omer echad zeh v’echad zeh soteim.
He's willing to be more lenient and he'll say either one does
a good job filling up a hole. בעי רב זירא: baei Rav
Zeira: רב זירא Rav Zeira said according to this idea that it’s
only the טהור חלב tahor chelev that fills up, חלב חיה מאי?
chelev chayah mai?
What about the חלב chelev of a חיה chayah like of a
deer where all of the חלב chelev is permissible? So would you
say that all of the חלב chelev does a good job of
filling up the hole? So what would you say? דווקא אמר חלב
טהור סותם והאי נמי טהור? davka amar chelev tahor soteim v’hai nami
tahor? Are you being really, you know, categorical and saying anything that's
not—that's kosher חלב chelev does a good job of filling up? So
this is also kosher. או דילמא משום דמהדק? o dilma mishum d’mehadeik?
Or no, it really has to do much more with the physical
characteristics that, you know, that it's the type of חלב chelev that's
sticky. והאי לא מהדק. v’hai lo mehadeik.
And the חלב chelev of a deer, the stuff that by a
cow would be טרפה but by a deer is kosher just by
virtue of it being a deer, that doesn't make the חלב chelev
any, you know, any more sticky or any less sticky. So therefore
in the case by the deer, the חלב chelev that would normally
be אסור assur by a cow also does not do—is not considered
to fill up holes, you know, in the case by the deer,
because it might be kosher but it's not sticky. So the answer
seems pretty obvious that it's all about being sticky, which is what
the גמרא says. אמר אביי מאי תיבעי ליה: amar Abaye mai tiba
lei: so אביי Abaye said what type of question was that? ניהי
דשרי באכילה, nihei d’shari b’achilah, it might be true that the deer
חלב chelev is permissible to eat, בהדוקי לא מהדק, bahadukei lo mehadeik,
but it's not sticky. So what type of silly question was that?
Because kosher was a way of identifying, you know, the different characteristics
of חלב chelev in the cow. But if it happens that everything
is kosher because it's in a deer, that doesn't make non-sticky חלב
chelev sticky, so it's still going to be a problem. Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot asks, by the way, says what the גמרא has not
discussed is the question about חלב chelev of birds. And what about
if the fat of birds? Will that fill up holes? And he
brings down a פסק psak here by רבינו יצחק Rabbeinu Yitzchak and
he said that
פשיטא דסותם דמהדק שפיר. p’shita d’soteim d’mehadeik shapir. The last line of
the תוספות חלב. Tosafot chelev. That there too if it's based on
the characteristic of stickiness, he used the—the fat of a bird, you
know, that was covering up a hole to say that that also
solved the problem. So here is a way to solve problems not
by סירכא but by חלב, chelev, at least the sticky חלב. chelev.
Okay, so now
the תורה Torah continues—the גמרא continues. Let's take a look. ההוא נקב
דסתמיה חלב טמא. hahu nekev d’sasmei chelev tamei.
There was a hole that was filled with חלב טמא, chelev tamei,
which again remember we said is not good. דאתא לקמיה דרבא. d’ata
l’kamei d’Rava. דאתא לקמיה דרבא, De-asa le-kamei de-Rava, came in front of
רבא. Rava. Now by the way, remember before there was one opinion
that said it was okay, but the dominant opinion so far has
been that it's not good. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא
Rava said, למאי ניחוש לה, Le-mai neichosh lah, why should we be
concerned about it? חדא, Chada, number one, דאמר רב ששת חלב טמא
נמי סותם. de-amar Rav Sheshes cheilev tamei nami soteim. There is an
opinion that of רב ששת Rav Sheshes said even טמא חלב tamei
cheilev stops a hole. ועוד, Ve-od, and number two, התורה חסה על
ממונם של ישראל. Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam shel Yisrael. We have a
general principle that the תורה's Torah concerned about loss of money for
the Jewish people. So since it's a case of הפסד, hefsed, let's
rule leniently and let's rule that even the חלב טמא cheilev tamei
solves the problem.
So אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא,
amar
lei
Rav Pappa le-Rava, so רב פפא Rav
Pappa said to רבא, Rava, רב ואיסורא דאורייתא ואת אמרת התורה חסה
על
ממונם של ישראל? Rav ve-issura de-Oraisa ve-at amart Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam
shel Yisrael? He says, first of all, we have the opinion of
רב that disagrees, it's so, you know, which is at least equally
debated, you know, weighed against רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, maybe even more
so because it seems to be the dominant position. And we're dealing
with an איסור דאורייתא. issur de-Oraisa. So we deal with an איסור
דאורייתא, issur de-Oraisa, you have to be מחמיר, machmir, you know, you're
not going to say if you have a reason that you really
פוסק pasken like ששת, Sheshes, don't worry. But you're not going to
say oh, it's a case of הפסד hefsed we'll be מיקל. meikel.
And you know, you say that by דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, you don't say
that by דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, by דאורייתא de-Oraisa you have to be מחמיר
machmir if you don't know who to פוסק pasken like. Okay, so
it's quite interesting that רבא Rava was felt the התורה חסה על
ממונם של ישראל Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam shel Yisrael as a very
big deal. What's his name?
Elman, Dr. Elman wrote a whole major, like, book almost that's like
a few hundred pages on רבא Rava and מחוזא, Mechuza, you know,
and רבא's Rava city, if I'm thinking if I remember correctly, and
about how, you know, questions about money and whatever and the people...
I forget the details. But anyway, it was something about he really,
you know, pointed to this issue about his sensitivity to causing people
loss of money had something to do with his dynamics with with
the community for whom he was פוסק. paskening. But I don't remember
any of the details, so עיין שם. ayein sham. Let's take a
look at one more story about this before we wrap up along
these lines. Okay, so the גמרא says like this:
בנימין קנדוקא, Minyomin Kanduka, so בנימין Minyomin who was
like a barrel owner or barrel seller or pitcher seller, אגלאי ליה
ביסטקא דדובשא. iglah lei bistaka de-duvsha. So a container of honey was
was uncovered. Now remember this problem about גילוי, giluy, if stuff is
left uncovered and unsupervised, we're afraid about the snake poison. Okay, so
אתא לקמיה דרבא. asa le-kamei de-Rava. He came to רבא. Rava. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said again the same thing, למאי
ניחוש לה, Le-mai neichosh lah, what do we have to be concerned
about? חדא דתנן שלשה משקין אסורין משום גילוי. Chada de-tenan sheloshah mashkin
asurin mishum giluy. We have a משנה Mishnah that says only three
liquids are a problem of being uncovered: היין והמים והחלב, Ha-yayin ve-ha-mayim
ve-ha-chalav,
wine and water and milk. ושאר כל המשקין מותרין. Ve-sha'ar kol ha-mashkin
mutarin. All other things are permissible. So according to this משנה, Mishnah,
honey is not a problem. ועוד, Ve-od, and number two, התורה חסה
על ממונם של ישראל, Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam shel Yisrael, let's not
forget that, it's a loss of money. So we should rule leniently
and we've got a משנה Mishnah to support it. So אמר ליה
רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא, amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak le-Rava,
so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said back to
רבא, Rava, רבי שמעון וסכנת נפשות ואת אמרת התורה חסה על ממונם
של ישראל? Rabbi Shimon ve-sakanas nefashos ve-at amart Ha-Torah chasah al mamonam
shel Yisrael? We have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has a dissenting opinion
and this is an issue, it might not be a דאורייתא, de-Oraisa,
but it's an issue of real danger to life. So you're going
to tell me oh we have to be concerned about money? We
have to be more concerned to be מחמיר machmir when it comes
to potential dangers. Who's the רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? So רבי שמעון
מאי, Rabbi Shimon mai, which is the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that's
strict? דתניא חמשה אין בהם משום גילוי. de-tanya chamishah ein bahem mishum
giluy. Five liquids don't have a problem of being uncovered: ציר חומץ
שמן ודבש ומוריס. tzir chometz shemen ve-dvash ve-muris. Fish brine, vinegar, oil,
honey, and מוריס, muris, which is also some type of a pickling
juice. רבי שמעון אומר אף הן יש בהם משום גילוי. Rabbi Shimon
omer af hein yesh bahem mishum giluy. Even those are a problem.
So you have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon being strict on honey. Now,
ואמר רבי שמעון, ve-amar Rabbi Shimon, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said,
אני ראיתי נחש ששתה ציר בצידון. ani ra'isi nachash she-shasah tzir be-Tzidon.
I saw a snake that drank actually the fish brine in צידון.
Tzidon. So you see these are problems about being uncovered, even these
weird liquids. סו אמרו לו, So amru lo, they said back to
him, שוטה היה. shoteh hayah. That was a stupid snake. ואין מביאין
ראיה מן השוטים. ve-ein mevivin ra'ayah min ha-shotim. And we don't take
proof from stupid
snakes. So, by the way, they tell there's a famous story they
tell in the name of רב Soloveitchik that the students wanted to
know if a toothpaste was a problem about for פסח, Pesach, apparently
it had some type of a, you know, some type of a
flour ingredient or whatever. He said, It's not ראוי לאכילת כלב. ra'uy
le-achilas kelev. So they decided they were going to do a test.
So they put some toothpaste on a plate and they and they
put in front of a dog and the dog licked it up.
So they came back to רב Soloveitchik. So according to one version
of the story, he said, It was a שוטה כלב, shoteh kelev,
like the שוטה נחש. shoteh nachash. According to the other version of
the story, which I actually like better, he said, Who's your רבי?
Me or the dog?
So anyway, okay, so that was the debate. סו אמר ליה, So
amar lei, so okay, so that's what he said
to רבא. Rava. So רבא Rava said back, he said, אודה לי
מיהא בציר. odei li mi-ha bi-tzir. At least admit to me that
we don't rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by the case of
the fish brine. They said he was a שוטה נחש, shoteh nachash,
at least admit that. If we don't rule like him by the
fish brine, presumably we don't rule like him by the honey either.
So דהא רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע ורבנן כי הוו
דלו גילויא שדו ליה *Deha Rav Papa v'Rav Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua
v'Rabbanan ki havo dalo giluya shadu leh* בציר *betzir* all these rabbis
when they had a case that they were concerned about גילוי *giluy*
they put it into this ציר *tzir* which would counteract the poison.
So at least you should admit that we don't rule like him
by the ציר *tzir* and if we don't rule like him by
the ציר *tzir* maybe not by the honey either.
So אמר ליה *amar leh* so he said back to רבא *Rava*
אודי לי מיהא בדבש *odi li miha bidvash* but you should at
least admit to me that we do rule that it's a problem
by honey. Why? רבי שמעון בן אלעזר קאי כוותיה *Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar kai kevatai*. So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*
not the same as רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* rules this way
like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. How do you know this? דתניא *detanya*
we taught a ברייתא *braita* וכן היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אוסר
בדבש *v'chen haya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar oser bidvash*. רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* forbade in the case of honey for
גילוי *giluy* so therefore you should have to be strict by honey
and forget don't tell me oh it's loss of money. It's all
very nice that we're concerned about loss of money but that's all
other things being equal not when you're dealing with things that are
דאורייתא *de'oraita* and not when you're dealing with things that are a
real question about danger. Now if one I should say that if
we're not for the last line that you had a specific פסק
*psak* like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* it's really you know in this
case it's much easier to understand what רבא *Rava* was doing because
you have a סתם משנה *stam mishna*. You have a סתם משנה
*stam mishna* doesn't mean that just because it's danger you have to
be concerned with every minority opinion. So you know this case at
least we really had a סתם משנה *stam mishna* going like him
but I guess given the end and in general we are a
little bit more you know we don't always go by strict rules
of פסק *psak* when it comes to danger issues but especially given
the end you see why the argument was that you need to
be strict here and you don't always weigh in favor of the
question about saving people from monetary loss which while it's a value
is not always the overriding value. Okay so we will end here
and pick up with this tomorrow in person. כל טוב *kol tuv*
everybody.